P. Phillips Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
P. Phillips Family Papers 1832-1914
MSS36087
Phillips, P (Philip), 1807-1884
7,000 items
22 containers
8.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, state legislator, and United States representative from Alabama. Correspondence, letter books, legal record books, journals, dockets, notebooks, and an unpublished autobiography of P. Phillips, relating chiefly to the law practice of P. Phillips and his son, W. Hallet Phillips, both of whom practiced before the Supreme Court. Contains the writings of P. Phillips's wife, Eugenia, including her journal written while interned during the Civil War, and of her parents, Jacob Clavius Levy and Fanny Yates Levy.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Campbell, James B., 1808-1883--Correspondence.; Dargan, Edmund Strother, 1805-1879--Correspondence.; Forsyth, John, 1780-1841--Correspondence.; Guthrie, George Wilkins, 1848-1917--Correspondence.; Harlan, John Marshall, 1833-1911--Correspondence.; King, William R. (William Rufus), 1786-1853--Correspondence.; Lamar, L. Q. C. (Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus), 1825-1893--Correspondence.; Levy, Fanny Yates, 1787-1891 or 1892. Fanny Yates Levy papers.; Levy, Jacob Clavius, 1788-1875. Jacob Clavius Levy papers.; Ludeling, John Theodore, 1827-1891--Correspondence.; Maury, William A. (William Arden), 1832-1918--Correspondence.; McCormick, Medill, 1877-1925--Correspondence.; Mordecai, M. C. (Moses Cohen), 1804-1888--Correspondence.; Olney, Richard, 1835-1917--Correspondence.; Phillips family.; Phillips, Eugenia Levy. Eugenia Levy Phillips journal. 1861-1862.; Phillips, P. (Philip), 1807-1884.; Phillips, W. Hallett (William Hallet), 1853-1897. W. Hallett Phillips papers.; Smith, Hoke, 1855-1931--Correspondence.; Stanton, Edwin M. (Edwin McMasters), 1814-1869--Correspondence.; Stickney, A. B. (Alpheus Beede), 1840-1916--Correspondence.; Yerger, William, 1816-1872--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States and Mexican Claims Commission.; United States. Kansas-Nebraska Act.; United States. Supreme Court.
Subjects
Courts--United States.; Hopi Indians.; Indians of North America--Arizona.; Justice, Administration of.; Lynching--Louisiana--Hahnville.; Missouri compromise.; National parks and reserves.; Practice of law--Washington (D.C.); Slave trade--United States.
Places
California--History.; Cuba--History--Revolution, 1895-1898.; Key West (Fla.)--History.; Mexico--Claims vs. United States.; United States--Claims vs. Mexico.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and prisons.; Yellowstone National Park.
Occupations
Lawyers.; Legislators--Alabama.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Alabama.
Provenance
The papers of P. Phillips, lawyer, state legislator, and United States representative from Alabama; his son, W. Hallett Phillips, lawyer; and other members of the Levy and Phillips families were obtained by gift, deposit, and purchase between 1900 and 1917 from P. Lee Phillips of Washington, D.C. In 1945 the remaining deposits were converted to a gift.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the P. Phillips family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
P. Phillips
Date Event
1807, Dec. 13 Born, Charleston, S.C.
1828 Admitted to bar
1832 Delegate to South Carolina State Constitutional Convention (nullification)
1833 1835 Member, South Carolina house of representatives
1836 Married Eugenia Yates Levy (died 1913)
1836 1853 Practiced law in Mobile, Ala.
1837 President, Alabama Democratic state convention
1844 Member, Alabama house of representatives
1850 Admitted to United States Supreme Court
1851 Member, Alabama house of representatives
1853 1855 Member, United States House of Representatives, 33rd Congress
1856 Began law practice in Washington, D. C.
1861 Wife, Eugenia Levy Phillips, interned for Confederate sympathies Family sent south to Crany Island via Fort Monroe as suspected spies for Confederate States of America. Began New Orleans, La., bar practice
1862 Wife, Eugenia Levy Phillips, confined to Ship Island as rebel spy and finally released by Benjamin Butler as prisoner of war after three months
1862 1866 Began law practice in La Grange, Ga., and New Orleans, La.
1867 Removed to Washington, D. C., and resumed United States Supreme Court practice
1884, Jan. 14 Died, Washington, D. C.
W. Hallett Phillips
Date Event
1853 Born, Washington, D. C.
1871 Graduated, Columbia College, Washington, D. C.
1885 1897 Special agent to investigate conditions in Yellowstone National Park
1887 Admitted to Supreme Court
1897 Drowned in Washington, D. C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the P. Phillips family span the period 1832 1914. The papers include the writings of Eugenia Levy Phillips and her parents, Jacob Clavius Levy and Fanny Yates Levy, but the bulk of the material relates to the law practice of her husband, P. Phillips (1807-1884), and his son, W. Hallett Phillips, prominent lawyers before the United States Supreme Court. Material concerning their practice is found primarily in the letterbooks, in the dockets, and in the legal record books. The collection is organized in eight series: Journal; General Correspondence, Letterbooks; Subject File; Autobiography, Speeches, and Writings; Legal File; Financial Papers; and Miscellany.
Although Eugenia Levy Phillips was an ardent Southerner, as shown in her journal written during her internment, P. Phillips apparently played an inactive role in the Civil War. There is a gap in the otherwise inclusive series of letterbooks for the period 1862 to 1867, but the period is scanned in his autobiography. Both P. Phillips and his son were champions of the disadvantaged. The elder Phillips was interested in California and the United States and Mexican Claims Commission, Key West and the slave trade, judicial reform, and in securing the repeal of the Missouri Compromise with the passage of the Kansas-Nebraska Act.
There is little biographical material on W. Hallett Phillips, but something of his character can be gleaned from his notebooks, translations and miscellaneous writings. His idealism is shown in material on the preservation of Yellowstone National Park, support of the Cuban revolution, investigation of a lynching at Hahnville, Louisiana, and the defense of the rights of the Moki (Hopi) Indians of Arizona.
Correspondence is generally on legal matters and includes James B. Campbell, Edmund Strother Dargan, John Forsyth, George Wilkins Guthrie, John Marshall Harlan, William R. King, William A. Maury, Medill McCormick, Moses Cohen Mordecai, Richard Olney, Hoke Smith, Edwin McMasters Stanton, A. B. Stickney, and William Yerger.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eight series:
Journal, 1861-1862
General Correspondence, 1832-1914
Letterbooks, 1856-1897
Subject File, 1885-1897
Autobiography, Speeches, and Writings, 1849-1884
Legal File, 1838-1897
Financial Papers, 1839-1890
Miscellany, 1850-1888
Container List
- Journal, 1861-1862 (Box 1)
  Holograph transcript and typed transcript of the journal of Eugenia Levy Phillips.
  - 1861, Aug.-Sept. (Box 1)
  - 1861-1862 (Box 1)
- General Correspondence, 1832-1914 (Box 1)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1832-1914 (Box 1)
- Letterbooks, 1856-1897 (Box 2-10)
  Washington, D. C. law office letterbooks of Philip Phillips; Phillips, Maury, & Phillips; W. Hallett Phillips; and Phillips & Phillips. There is some overlapping between volumes and a gap in the records of Philip Phillips for the period 1862-1867.
  Arranged by name of firm and chronologically thereunder.
  - Philip Phillips (Box 2)
    - 1856, Feb.-1869, Dec. (Box 2)
    - 1870, Jan.-1873, Sept. (Box 3)
    - 1873, Sept.-1877, Mar. (Box 4)
    - 1877, Mar.-1882, May (Box 5)
  - Phillips, Maury, & Phillips, 1877, Apr.-1883, Nov. (Box 6)
  - W. Hallett Phillips, 1875, Aug.-1885, June; Phillips & Phillips, 1883-1884 (Box 7)
  - W. Hallett Phillips (Box 8)
    - 1885, June-1889, Mar. (Box 8)
    - 1889, Mar.-1893, Mar. (Box 9)
    - 1893, Mar.-1897, May (Box 10)
- Subject File, 1885-1897 (Box 11-12)
  Correspondence, reports, and printed matter.
  Arranged by subject or type of material.
  - Cuban Revolution, 1895-1896 (Box 11)
  - Hahnville, La., lynching 1896 (Box 11)
  - Judiciary Reform Bill, 1890-1892 (Box 11)
  - Wharton, Digest of International Law, 1896-1897 (Box 12)
  - Yellowstone National Park, 1885-1897 (Box 12)
- Autobiography, Speeches, and Writings, 1849-1884 (Box 13-14)
  Autobiography, printed speeches and statements, and "In Memoriam," of P. Phillips, and miscellaneous writings and translations of W. Hallett Phillips.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Autobiography of P. Phillips, circa 1870-1876 (Box 13)
  - Speeches by P. Phillips, 1849-1861 (Box 13)
  - "In Memoriam" of P. Phillips, 1884 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous writings, notes, and translations of W. Hallett Phillips (Box 14)
- Legal File, 1838-1897 (Box 15-17)
  Deeds, will, Supreme Court brief, dockets, legal notebooks, and record books of Philip Phillips; Phillips, Maury, & Phillips; and W. Hallett Phillips.
  - Deeds (Box 15)
  - Supreme Court brief, Key v. Frelinghuysen, undated (Box 15)
  - Will of Jacob Clavius Levy, 1870 (Box 15)
  - Docket book of W. Hallett Phillips, 1867-1878 (Box 16)
  - Docket book of Philip Phillips; Phillips, Maury, & Phillips; and W. Hallett Phillips, 1875-1880 (Box 16)
  - Index and digest of Wallace's Reports, United States Supreme Court, 1877 (Box 16)
  - Docket of United States Supreme Court (Box 16)
  - Legal notebooks of P. Phillips, (2 vols.) (Box 16)
  - Legal notebook of W. Hallett Phillips (Box 16)
  - Record book (Box 17)
    - Philip Phillips, 1838-1858 (Box 17)
    - Phillips and Maury, 1855-1861 (Box 17)
    - Phillips & Phillips, 1883 (Box 17)
    - W. Hallett Phillips, 1884-1897 (Box 17)
    - Phillips, Maury, & Phillips, 1877-1882 (Box 17)
- Financial Papers, 1839-1890 (Box 18-19)
  Ledger, account books, receipt books, cancelled checks, and fee memorandum.
  - Ledger (Box 18)
    - Gayle & Phillips, circa 1839-1841 (Box 18)
    - Philip Phillips, circa 1855-1861 (Box 18)
  - Account book (Box 18)
    - Philip Phillips (Box 18)
      - 1843-1862 (Box 18)
      - 1862-1873 (Box 18)
    - Philip Phillips and Phillips & Phillips, 1867-1885 (Box 18)
  - Receipt book (Box 19)
  - Philip Phillips, 1842-1852 (Box 19)
  - Checks, 1845-1883 (Box 19)
  - Fee memorandum, 1890 (Box 19)
- Miscellany, 1850-1888 (Box 20-22)
  Commonplace books, receipt books, scrapbooks and notebooks, a copy of "Vindiciae Judaeorum," a book of quotations, notes and invitations, memorabilia, photographs, and printed matter.
  - Commonplace book, Fanny Yates Levy (Box 20)
  - Commonplace book, W. Hallett Phillips (Box 20)
  - Receipt book, P. Phillips (Box 20)
  - Memoirs of an Hungarian Lady, by Theresa Pulszky (Philadelphia, 1850) (Box 20)
  - Receipt book, poetry, and related material, Samuel Yates Levy, 1857-1871 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, P. Phillips, 1860-1863 (Box 21)
  - Legal notebook, W. Hallett Phillips, 1871, undated (Box 21)
  - Memorabilia, 1850-1887 (Box 21)
  - Notebook, W. Hallett Phillips (Box 22)
  - "Vindicise Judaeorum," by Jacob C. Levy, 1861 (Box 22)
  - Book of quotations, W. Hallett Phillips, 1875 (Box 22)
  - Photographs (Box 22)
  - Printed matter (Box 22)